Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Reports
  - Working Papers of the International Study of Opinion-Makers,vol. III. Edited by Bogdan Denitch, June, 1970 (Box 132, Folder B-1085-3)
    [1. Political Cultures and Social Mobility in Yugoslavia. Bogdan Denitch, 34 pp.; 2 Social Mobility of the Opinion-Makers in Yugoslavia. Radomir Lukic, 7 pp.; 3 Mobility and Recruitment of Yugoslav Leadership: The Role of the League of Communists. Bogdan Denitch, 22 pp.; 4 The Relationship Between Public 0pinion-Makers and Public Opinion. Mladen Zvonarovic, 17 pp.; 5 Several Hypotheses in Connection with the Social Origin and Functional Characteristics of the Yugoslav Political Elite. Rudi Supek, 22 pp.; 6 Power Structure of Statist and Self-Governing Socialism. Rudi Supek, 25 pp.; 7 Democratization and its Effect on Elite Group Relations. Rudi Supek, 38 pp.; 8 Some Values, Attitudes and Opinions of Opinion-Makers. Dragomir Pantic, 11 pp.; 9 Cultural Reproduction and Social Reproduction. Pierre Bourdieu, 44 pp.; 10 Preliminary Bibliography of English-Language Studies of National Leaders and Opinion-Makers. Allen Barton, 15 pp. NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Ideology and Opinion-Making-General Problems of Analysis. Helen McClure and George Fischer, 1969, ( 60 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1085-4)
    [ (Revised version is part of ch.1 of George Fischer, Ways to Self-Rule, Hicksville, N.Y.: Exposition, 1978. NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Conference on Theory and Method in Comparative Elite Analysis. Edited by Louis Edinger, April, 1969 (Box 132, Folder B-1085-5)
  - College Volunteer Workers: A First Look at Goal Priority, Achievement, Satisfaction, and Turnover in Four Volunteer Job Statuses. Harry Slan, 1968, ( 26 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder S-1085)
  - Attitudes of Selected Small Samples of Negroes Toward Jews and Other Ethnic Groups. Carolyn 0. Atkinson, 1968, ( 107 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1086)
    [The purpose of this study was to determine the content and dimensions of Blacks' attitudes toward Jews, as Blacks from various economic classes representing four distinctive life styles were interviewed. NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Readers of Africa Report: Their Views and Characteristics. W. Phillips Davison and Henri Verwayen, 1967, ( 40 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1087)
    [An examination of readers in the United States and Africa of a specialized publication on Africa, based on mail questionnaires from 721 readers.]
  - The Merchants of Harlem: A Study of Small Business in a Black Community. David Caplovitz, Lois Sanders, Bernard Levenson and Joan Wilson, 1969, ( 220 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder *B-1089)
    [This is based on interviews with 125 black and 106 white businessmen in Central Harlem and 53 in Bay Ridge, a white middle-class area. It compares the black and white merchants generally with the Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, merchants, to learn whether race or other factors account for differences in their experiences. Published: Beverly Hills, CA: Sage Publications, 1973.]
  - Toward A Theory of Applied Sociology. Paul F. Lazarsfeld and Jeffrey G. Reitz, 1970, ( 78 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-1)
  - The Consequences of the Study of Federal Student Loan Programs. Carol Weiss, 1970, ( 133 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-2)
  - Some Problems in the Organization and Use of Social Research in the U.S. Navy. Douglas C. McDonald with Introduction by Paul F. Lazarsfeld, 1972, ( 147 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-3)
  - The Utilization of Basic Social Research-A Case Study. Joel I. Brooke, 1972, ( 175 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-4)
  - The Gap Between Knowledge and Decision in the Utilization of Social Research. Jeffrey Reitz, 1973, ( 34 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder *B-1090-5)
    [Published as ch. 5 of P. F. Lazarsfeld and J. G. Reitz, An Introduction to Applied Sociology, New York: Elsevier, 1975. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - A Survey of Social Researchers' Attitudes Toward Utilization. Joel I. Brooke, 1973, ( 30 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-6)
  - The Road to Recommendations. Ann K. Pasanella and Janice Weinman, 1973, ( 98 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-7)
  - Social Interaction Between Policy Makers and Social Scientists. Jeffrey G. Reitz, 1973, ( 48 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder *B-1090-8)
    [Published as ch. 6 of An Introduction to Applied Sociology.]
  - Futurism. Alfred Oxenfeldt, 1973, ( 42 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-9)
  - Some Problems of Research Organization. Douglas McDonald and Paul F. Lazarsfeld, 1973, ( 67 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-10)
  - Formal Approaches to Applied Social Research. Norman P. Hummon and Patrick Doreian, 1975, ( 89 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1090-11)
    [This project studies the utilization of social research.]
  - The Community Patrol Corps: A Descriptive Evaluation of the One-Week Experiment. George Nash, 1968, ( 73 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1092)
    [This report describes and evaluates the one-week experiment of the Community Patrol Corps (made up of male residents between the ages of 18-30) patrolling areas of Harlem. The participants and their experiences are presented as well as the response to the Corps from the community, press, police and city officials. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - The Nature of the Student Movement and Radical Proposals for Change at Columbia University. Camilla Auger, Allen Barton and Raymond Maurice, 1969, ( 57 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1093)
    [Report on a survey of student opinion in the fall of 1968, a few months after the uprising of 1968. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Design for the Use of Survey Research in the Evaluation of the Impact of the Model-Cities Program on the Residents of Model-City Neighborhoods. Joan Gordon, Gladys Meyer, Roland Wulbert, Carol Weiss and Allen Barton, 1968, ( 124 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1095)
    [This report considers the several faces of poverty, discusses what should be considered in constructing measures of the "quality of life," introduces the methodological issues, spells out the main variables to be included in survey instruments, presents a basic sampling design and some variants, and considers the special problems of interviewing low-income groups.]
  - Homeless Women in New York City: Observations at the Emergency Assistance Unit and Women's Shelter. Gerald R. Garrett and Dinah Hirschfeld Volk, 1970, ( 78 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1096-1)
  - Patterns and Implications of Women's Work: A Research Review. Marcia Garrett, 1970, ( 100 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1096-2)
  - Disaffiliation Among Aged Women: The Novelists' View. Marcia J. Cebulski, Laura Kemp, Dorothy Frost, and Susan Rutherford Muller, 1970, ( 43 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1096-3)
  - Disaffiliation Among Urban Women. Howard M. Bahr and Gerald R- Garrett under the direction of Theodore Caplow, 1971, ( 463 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder *B-1096-4)
    [This is an extension of previous work (see B-1024). 331 middle-aged and elderly socially isolated women from 3 census tracts in Manhattan and 52 who were clients of a shelter for homeless women were interviewed. The personal and social consequences of human isolation were explored; whether the process is reversible or permanent, voluntary or forced; the role of organizations in the development and prevention of disaffiliation; and how it relates to other individual and community problems. Published as Women Alone. The Disaffiliation of Urban Females. Lexington, MA: Lexington Books, D. C. Heath & Co., 1976. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Small-Project Grants of the Regional Research Program. Theresa F. Rogers, Lois W. Sanders and Bernard Levenson, 1970, ( 175 pp. ) (Box 132, Folder B-1098)
    [Under the Office of Education's RRP, proposals up to $ 10,000 are submitted to the office in the researcher's geographic area. The distribution of applicants, the processing of proposals and the consequences of being funded were examined. Data were collected by questionnaires to applicants and to those who reviewed proposals, factual materials abstracted from proposals, ratings of them and funding recommendations, and interviews with the Directors of Educational Research at the nine offices.]
  - The Quality of Research on Education: An Empirical Study of Researchers and Their Work Caroline H. Persell, 1971, ( 417 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder *B-1099)
    [ The focus of this project was the quality of research on education, and the characteristics and experiences of researchers which were related to research quality. The quality of all papers read at the 1968 American Educational Research Association meeting and all education-related research articles published in 113 journals in 1967-68 was rated by a national panel of 40 eminent researchers. Additionally, the authors of the papers were surveyed and their undergraduate academic achievement, graduate training, career lines, research settings, and professional rewards were analyzed in relation to the quality of their research. A series of "models" was developed to explain variation in quality. Published as: Quality, Careers and Training in Education and Social Research. Bayside, N.Y.: General Hall, 1976.]
  - Coverage of Minority Group Affairs in the New York News Media and the Black Evaluation: A Pilot Study. Robert Hill, Sally Howlett, Kenneth J. Lenihan and George Nash, 1969, ( 122 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1101)
    [ This is a report on the findings of a preliminary study to determine how much mass media coverage was being given to minority groups in the New York area and what the principal reactions to this coverage were on the part of the minority groups themselves. 53 influential Blacks were interviewed as were 2 panels of 20 Blacks each.]
  - The Federal Educational Opportunity Grant Program: A Status Report, Fiscal Year 1970. Nathalie Friedman with the assistance of James Thompson, 1971, ( 352 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1106)
    [The Federal Educational Opportunity Grant Program provides grants to low-income students to attend college, 70% of whose families have annual incomes of less than $6,000. Data for the study were gathered from questionnaires answered by 9,789 students; information on 10,166 students supplied by aid administrators; 1,620 questionnaires from participating institutions; interviews with administrators and students at 20 institutions; and government reports. The report includes recommendations to strengthen the successful program.]
  - Problems in the Evaluation of Mental Health Projects, Proceedings of a Seminar. Carol H. Weiss, chairman, and Sally T. Hillsman, 1970, ( 37 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1107)
    [This is a presentation of a case study of evaluation conducted within an operating program and the group discussion of the issues and solutions. REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - The Student Brain Drain, A Report to the Ford Foundation. Paul Ritterband and Seymour Warkov, 1973, ( 98 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1108)
    [(A joint report with the Center for Policy Research.) This discusses the problem of students who study in developed countries, and then do not return to their homelands to work and apply their knowledge to the developing countries' benefit REPORT NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Community Response to a Narcotic Addiction Treatment Facility: The Case of Prospect Place. George Nash, 1969, ( 24 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1117)
    [This study examines how residents felt about a narcotic treatment facility one year after it opened despite some initial community opposition. 91 community residents were interviewed.]
  - The Federal College Work Study Program: A Status Report, Fiscal Year 1971. Nathalie Friedman, Lois Sanders and James Thompson, 1973, ( 430 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1119)
    [Some 10,000 students, 2,000 institutions of higher education, and 2,200 employers participating in the College Work Study Program during the academic year l970-1971 were studied. The characteristics of students and their employment settings are described and components of students' job satisfaction are analyzed. Aid officers' and employers' problems in administering the program are analyzed. An extensive bibliography is included.]
  - The Use of Educational Knowledge. Sam D. Sieber, Karen Seashore Louis and Loya Metzger, 1972, Two Volumes, ( 1,100 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder *B-1120)
    [This two-year study details the process and outcomes of extension agent work and computerized information retrieval in a major, three-state tryout of a new educational dissemination system supported by the U.S. Office of Education. Case studies cover the tactics and problems of field agents in conveying information and supporting innovation within school settings. Results of extension agent and retrieval practices at all levels of local educational structures are examined. Instruments and guidelines for evaluation and monitoring of E&R projects are included. (Available from ERIC Document Reproduction Service, PO Box 190, Arlington, Virginia, Nos. ED 065.739 and ED 065 740.)]
  - Abstracts of Papers on Respondent-Interviewer Interaction in the Research Interview. Laurie Bauman, Theresa Rogers and Carol Weiss, 1971, ( 152 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1121-1)
    [This report presents abstracts of papers in order to bring to the attention of researchers the available evidence (and in some cases, theories and speculations) on the effects of respondent-interviewer interaction on research data.]
  - The Use of Indigenous Interviewers in Survey Research: Progress Report to the National Center for Health Services Research and Development. Theresa F. Rogers, Laurie J. Bauman and Carol H. Weiss, 1971, ( 57 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1121-2)
    [This is based on pilot interviews prior to the questionnaire survey. NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Practices of Research Organizations in Surveys of the Poor. Carol H. Weiss, Laurie J. Bauman and Theresa F. Rogers, 1973, ( 70 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1121-3)
    [An intensive search for interview surveys of low-income populations turned up 194 recent samples. These were examined to assess the benefits and limitations of using racially and economically similar interviewers in surveys of the poor. Characteristics of interviewers, recruitment, training, supervision, and the study directors' assessment of interviewer performance were analyzed.]
  - Employment Prospects in the Educational System for Unemployed Engineers, Scientists, and Other Highly Qualified Technical Personnel. A. J. Jaffe and Walter Adams., 1971, (33 pp. and 40 pp. Preliminary and Final Reports for Summer 1971.) (Box 133, Folder B-1126-1,2)
  - Extent of Engineers' Interest in Jobs in the Educational Establishment-Final Report, December l971. A. J. JaffeandWalterAdams, 1971, ( 19 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1126-3)
    [This study made use of questionnaires to samples of colleges, universities, public high schools, engineers and scientists. NOT AVAILABLE]
  - Too Little and Too Late-The Economic Plight of Very Seriously and Permanently Disabled Men and Their Households in the New York City Metropolitan Area. WalterAdams and A. J. Jaffe, 1972, ( 132 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1128)
    [This study focuses upon a group of metropolitan area men with extremely serious permanent job-related disabilities which occurred in the latter 1960s. Respondents were interviewed in the first quarter of 1972. Emphasis is placed upon the adequacy of Workmen's Compensation benefits, as well as a number of other sources of household funds in the years immediately following disability. Non-financial changes in life-circumstances and styles were also documented at length.]
  - Attention to Population on the Campus. Theresa F. Rogers with the assistance of Laurie J. Bauman, 1974, ( 144 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1129)
    [This examines the place that population occupies in undergraduate education both in the classroom and in extracurricular activities. It is based on information collected in 1972 from more than a dozen campuses across the country that differ markedly in the attention that population receives. The report covers population in the curriculum, alternative strategies for teaching population, the overlay of values and attitudes that affect instruction, extracurricular activities related to population, and gives conclusions and recommendations.]
  - New York City Neighborhood Project Reports. This study was designed to evaluate the effect on citizens of experiments in decentralization carried out by the city. Samples of residents and community leaders were interviewed two years apart. Field observations and unstructured interviewing of administrators, and case studies of particular agencies were also carried out. The project ran from 1972 to 1975., 1972-1975 (Box 133, Folder B-1131)
  - Between Community and City Bureaucracy: New York's District Manager Experiment. Stanley J. Heginbotham, et al., 5 parts, 1973, (416 pp. Interim Report) (Box 133, Folder B-1131-25)
  - Interim Report: Experimental Study of Decision Making in the 12versus 6-Man Jury under Unanimous versus Non-unanimous Decisions. Alice Padawer-Singer and Allen H. Barton, 1975, ( 138 pp. ) (Box 134, Folder B-1137)
    [This is an experimental study of the problem of the 12- vs. 6-man jury and of unanimous vs. non-unanimous decisions, conducted with an actual population of jurors, in the courts, with the collaboration of members of the judiciary, the bar, and the social sciences. Ninety-two experimental juries have been run, 23 under each of the four combinations of jury size and unanimous/non-unanimous decision.]
  - Employment of Women and Fertility. A. J. Jaffe and J. C. Ridley (of Georgetown University), 1976, ( 99 pp. ) (Box 134, Folder B-1142)
    [Data from censuses and surveys covering 1910-1970 were analyzed to determine the relationship among education, labor force participation and fertility of women in the United States.]
  - Union Involvement and Citizen Duty. R. Wayne Parsons, 1976, ( 114 pp. ) (Box 134, Folder B-1144)
    [Interviews with 393 rank and file members and 108 "active members" of a large city public employees union were analyzed to discover the effect of union involvement in political attitudes and behavior. A supplementary sample of 55 union officers and staff members were also interviewed concerning their own union careers.]
  - Some Demographic and Economic Characteristics of the Puerto Rican Population Living on the Mainland, USA. A. J. Jaffe and Zaida Carleton, 1974, ( 79 pp. ) (Box 134, Folder B- 1145)
    [The study, using 1960 and 1970 census data, covers social, economic, and housing conditions. Puerto Ricans living in New York State are contrasted with those living in other states.]
  - The Doctor Under National Health Insurance: Foreign Lessons for the United States. William A. Glaser, 1977, ( 429 pp. ) (Box 134, Folder B-1148)
    [Topics covered are how to organize insurance carriers and medical associations; how to organize negotiations between them; costs and how to contain them; work schedules of doctors; how to improve primary care, preventive medicine, and long term care; effects of different reimbursement and administrative arrangements on the recruitment and location of doctors; and how to write fee schedules. Chapters I through X have been published as Health Insurance Bargaining: Foreign Lessons for Americans, New York: Gardner Press, 1978. The.microfiche edition contains only Chapters XI through XV.]
- Series IV: Masters Essays
  All Masters Essays were submitted to the Department of Sociology of Columbia University. For interlibrary loan, contact Interlibrary Loan Service, Columbia University Libraries. For purchase of microfilm or Xerox copies, contact the Photographic Service Department, Columbia University Libraries.
  - (Box 134)
  - Dependence, Cooperation, and Conflict: Assumptions and Realities in Local Service Integration. John M. Boyle and Stanley J. Heginbotham, 1975, ( 35 pp. ) (Box 133, Folder B-1131-27)
- Series V: Doctoral Dissertations
  Boxes 135-136. Doctoral Dissertations were submitted to the Sociology Department of Columbia University. All Columbia dissertations are available on interlibrary loan; address requests to Interlibrary Loan Service, Columbia University Libraries. Those available on microfilm are so designated and may be purchased directly from University Microfilms, Ann Arbor, Michigan.
  - Hillsman, Sally T. Entry into the Labor Market: The Preparation and Job Placement of Negro and White Vocational High School Graduates, 1970, (539 pp. ) (Box 135, Folder D-8001)
    [Dissertation proposal copy]
  - Camilla Auger Fluidics: A Study of the Growth Pattern of a New technology, 1968-1970, (3 Folders Folders Contain: Proposal (August, 1968)-10 pp., Progress Report (March, 1970)-12 pp.and Request for Continued Research Permission (April, 1970)-9 pp.) (Box 135, Folder D-8002)
  - Margit A. Johansson The Differential Effects of Reduced Research Funding on University Scientists, 1970, (One Folder Fact Sheet and Questionnaires) (Box 135, Folder D-8003)
  - David, Deborah S. Career Patterns and Values: A Study of Men and Women in Science and Engineering, 1969, (278 pp. 2 copies and draft paper entitled "Value Differences of Women Scientists & Engineers,", 1971, 7 pp., 2 copies. ) (Box 135, Folder D-8004)
  - Richard H. B. Mendes The professional Union: A Study of the Social Services Employees Union of the New York City Department of Social Services, 1969, (Three Folders, Qustionnaires and some Chapters. ) (Box 135, Folder D-8005)
    [Cross-referenced with S-1095.]
  - Reitz, Jeffrey The Flight from Science: Student Disillusionment with Careers in Science and Engineering, 1972, (203 pp. ) (Box 135, Folder D-8006)
  - Sherry Gorelick Incentives & Obstacles to Management Hiring of the Disadvantaged, 1970's (?), (One Folder Fact Sheet only.) (Box 135, Folder D-8007)
  - Elisabeth Gemberling, Margaret Nelson in collaboration with Sam D. Sieber The Role of Secondary Education in the Development of Indigenous Leadership in American Indian Communities, 1970-1973, (Four Foldersand One Book Book and First folder are both copies of the Final Report (218 pp. plus appendices). Other Folder scontain 2 copies of Master"s Essay Entitled "An Analytic Framework for the 1968 Study," (1973)-55 pp. -2 copies, Proposal (1969), Codebooks and Questionnaires..) (Box 135, Folder D-8008)
  - Single, Eric Sociological Aspects of Debt Entanglement, 1970-1971, (One bound BASR Report and Two Folders Bound Report and One folder contain thesis -276 pp. -(2 copies), while second folder contains Proposal and Abstract (1970)-6 pp.) (Box 136, Folder D-8009)
    [Based on B-1060]
  - Rodriguez, Orlando Social Determinants of Non-Return: A Study of Foreign Students from Developing Countries in the United States, 1974, (One book and One Folder Book and folder contain identical copies of the thesis-(199 pp.each) (Box 136, Folder D-8011)
    [Based on B-1108]
  - Nelson, Margaret K. The Adoption of Innovations in Urban Schools, 1975-1976, (One book and three Folders Book is original copy of thesis (march, 19750. First Folder is revised version of thesis (February, 1976)- each is 306 pp. Other folder scontain Proposal entitled 'Innovation in :Large City High Schools, by Nelso and Sieber and article (1976) cross referneced to record A-724.) (Box 136, Folder D-8012)
- Series VI: Articles